# 今天咱们做一个剁椒蒸鱼
Today we are making a steamed fish with fermented chopped red pepper.
# 蒸鱼头
I meant to say fish head.
# 这个是花鲢
This is a calyx.
# 这个有好重四伯爷你看
Uncle, guess how much does the fish weigh?
# 四五斤吧
2-2.5 kg.
# 对 四斤半左右
Correct, around 2.25 kg.
# 先把它敲一下
Stun the fish on the head.
# 咱们这个剁椒蒸鱼头
To steam a fish head,
# 大家不会改刀的
If you don’t know how to cut the meat
# 现在可以看一下斜着改
You can try to cut it this way with angle
# 这样子斜着改它鱼头翻过来了之后呢
Then when you flip the fish over
# 它这个头就圆圆的
The head will be round
# 这样子
Like this
# 然后咱们在市场上面买的鱼头
The fish head we can buy from the market
# 商贩也会这样子他斜的很厉害
The fish sellers usually will cut with a big angle
# 可能这样子斜对半
Like 45 degrees
# 因为鱼头偏贵一些
Because fish head is usually the more pricy part,
# 鱼尾的话就卖得便宜些
Fishtail is cheaper.
# 我们就斜着把鱼肚都留在上面
I cut it this way to keep all the fish belly
# 伯爷喜欢吃
Uncle loves this part
# 然后再翻过来
Now I flip it over
# 这样子
Like this.
# 但是大家一定要小心
Please note that
# 不能直接把它剁开
You don’t want to just simply cut it open
# 剁开了它的内脏的话就出来了
That will have all the organs running out
# 就不好看
It won’t look nice.
# 到这个位置
From here
# 这个位置的话给它剁下去
Chop down from here
# 它的脊椎就到这个位置
Where the spine is.
# 很多同学在问这个鱼头怎么破
Many asked me, how to cut the fish head into half
# 破哪一边
Which side to cut from
# 有人会说选择破肚子这边
Some say to cut from the bottom side
# 其实破肚子非常难看
It actually would look really ugly
# 我们必须从这边破下去
We’d better cut from this way
# 这边破开了非常好看
It will look great.
# 慢慢的这样子走过去
Cut it slowly and carefully.
# 如果你是买的话
If you just buy the fish head
# 尽量让摊主给你处理好
Have the seller to cut and clean it for you
# 好 这样子扳开
OK, now we open it like this
# 扳开了之后我们再来去它的内脏
Then we get rid of its organs
# 这是它的鱼胆 鱼肝 鱼肠之类的
Like the gallbladder, liver, and intestines, etc
# 不要
Discard them.
# 像上次杀那个鲤鱼一样
Just like what we did last time with the carp
# 好 我们鱼头就改好了
Now the fish head is ready
# 现在去清洗一下
We will rinse it
# 现在我们这个鱼清洗干净了
Now it is rinsed clean
# 但是还有一个地方没有去除
But I noticed one more thing to remove
# 它的这个牙齿
Its teeth
# 在这个位置
It’s located here.
# 大头鱼的都在这个位置
Teeth of bighead fishes are all here
# 这个鱼头改一下刀
Now we give the fish head some cuts
# 就是说在上面随便的剁一下
Just a few random slices is fine
# 剁一下就让它这个味道更容易进去
The seasonings will soak in better
# 下面我们来随便腌制一下
Now let’s do a simple marinade
# 简单的腌制
Very simple
# 撒一点点这个盐
A little bit salt
# 不用太多一点点就行
Just a little bit
# 因为剁椒也是咸的
Because the fermented red pepper is very salty
# 好 腌制了给它放在一边
Now let’s set it aside.
# 好 现在来处理这个剁椒
We are going to process the pepper.
# 这个就是湖南本地的一个剁椒
It is a brand from Hunan.
# 其实价格很便宜不贵
Price is very reasonable.
# 大家可以看下这个剁椒
Let’s take a look at it
# 它原来的水是非常咸的
The brine water is very salty
# 而且有一股发酵的味道
With a fermented smell.
# 现在我们要把它清洗一下
So we need to rinse it
# 把它清洗过呀
You rinse the pepper?
# 要洗过 不是那个味道有点怪
It is necessary, it smells.
# 这个我们洗个一两次就可以了
One or two times rinsing is good enough
# 如果这个剁椒里面水太多啊
If the pepper is not drained completely
# 它这个蒸出来就是有一股水的味道
It will smell watery later.
# 香味就出不来
And the aroma will not come out.
# 好 然后我们这个剁椒里面配一点蒜
Now we need to add some garlic to the pepper
# 就是给它剁碎了放进去
Some minced garlic
# 切一点这个姜片
Then some ginger slices
# 垫在鱼下面
Place the slices under the fish.
# 它蒸的时候自己可以去除一些腥味
It is to get rid of the fishy smell
# 这个葱就把它挽起来就可以了
Tie the green onions into a knot
# 现在我们要准备开始做了
Now we are ready to steam it.
# 就把这个姜片垫在下面
Put the ginger slices on the bottom
# 然后再放上这个葱
Then the green onion
# 最后我们来把这个鱼头放到这个上面
Last we put the fish head on it
# 这样子的话
thus
# 它那个就有利于它的水呀
All the liquid
# 蒸汽水啊 它的血水啊
Like the steam and blood..
# 流到盘子底下
Will stay at the bottom of the plate
# 待会我们是吧
During the steaming
# 蒸的时候就可以把那个水去一去
We can pour some liquid out
# 好 我去烧火准备蒸起了
Now I am going to start the burner
# 要得
Okay
# 锅头是菜籽油呀
Is this rapeseed oil?
# 菜籽油 你打的那个都嘛
Yes, the oil you made.
# 这个要下去炒哈
You need to fry these?
# 炒了之后就更香这个
Yes, they are more flavorful once fried.
# 那肯定了
Sure it is.
# 油多点好吃点
More oil will make it tastier.
# 鱼肯定要油多点才好吃
Fish dish needs more cooking oil.
# 整得干巴巴的就不安逸了
It doesn’t taste good if it is dry.
# 盐巴 一滴滴的就够了
As for salt, a little bit is enough.
# 放点鸡精
Some chicken bouillon powder
# 放点这个白糖
Some sugar
# 少放一滴滴的蚝油
And some oyster sauce
# 稍微炒一哈就可以放在这个上来了
Slightly fry it and then pour on the fish
# 好 十分钟
OK, 10 minutes
# 先撒一半的葱花
Sprinkle half of the green onion on it.
# 过一下油之后再撒剩下的一半
Pour some oil over the green onions, then sprinkle the rest afterward
# 葱葱撒起 稀稀疏疏的看到还舒服
Some green makes it look nice.
# 在给它撒一点
Some more.
# 好 可以吃了
OK, now it’s ready to serve
# 试一哈
Let’s try it
# 管他对不对哦
Doesn’t matter if every step is perfectly authentic
# 先整来试哈
I will try it
# 你先尝一下够不够盐味
Try if it is salty enough
# 不够盐味我们再淋一点酱油上去
If not, we can add some soy sauce.
# 酱油最后淋上去才好吃
Soy sauce must be added after cooking.
# 伯爷 吃鱼头要吃前面
Uncle, the meat in the front is the best.
# 我先把这个吃了 尝一下味道
I am just testing if it’s salty enough.
# 先从这个鱼嘴这里吃起走
It’s better to start from the fish lips.
Start eating from the fish lip.
# 这个才是最滑的
It tastes smooth and nice.
# 来 伯娘
Help yourself, aunti-in-law.
# 好好好 没得事的
Ok ok ok, no worries
# 安逸
It tastes great.
# 够不够味道
Salty enough?
# 够味道
Yes
# 够了 是不是
Enough flavors?
# 嗯
Yes.
# 嗯 够了
Enough indeed.
# 因为我们这个剁椒可能偏咸一点点
Fermented pepper usually is on the saltier side.
# 如果说洗完之后不够味的话
But after rinsing, it might not be as salty.
# 最后我们再淋一点这个酱油就可以了
In that case, we just need to add some soy sauce.
# 真的安逸
It tastes really nice!
# 它和豆花一样
As tender as tofu pudding.
# 就是油要多点稍微
It needs more oil than other dishes.
# 嗯
Yes.
# 如果油少了蒸出来就是干巴巴的这个肉
If the oil is not enough, the steamed fish will taste dry.
# 本来整鱼就要鱼（的）油多
All fish dishes require more oil in general.
# 嗯 是
Oh, that’s right.
# 我伯爷都说很好吃
My uncle says it tastes really good
# 嗯 很好吃
Yes, very flavorful.
# 大家可以在家里试一下
You can try to cook this at home.
# 我伯爷说了评价这个湘菜当中的剁椒鱼头
My uncles say the steamed fish head with fermented red pepper
# 名不虚传
Is really matching its fame.
# 嗯 安逸
Yes, really nice.
# 好吃
Tasty!
# 赞不绝口
Can’t praise it enough.
# 好了 本期视频就到这里
OK, that’s all for today’s video.